I'm just going to make a quick video
somebody was asking me about is Java
compiled and I I want to give a
breakdown of the different types of
languages really quick I haven't I know
I've been kind of depressed because I've
been writing this book and everything
but let me give you something of value
so when it comes to programming
languages there are many many many kinds
of languages just like there are many
kinds of tools to do things that I think
that goes without saying but they they
generally break down into two categories
and I'm going to go out on a limb
somebody's going to yell at me but
scripting languages you know dynamically
typed interpreted scripting languages
and compiled languages or strictly
statically typed compiled language now
at the core I'm going to be very
pedantic about this all languages are
compiled what does that mean that means
that when you write code that code
doesn't run on the computer until it
becomes machine code and you can write
machine code if you want but it's like
that's the whole thing about high and
level and low and all that is how close
is the language you're writing to
assembly that's what they mean the lower
the language the closer it is to
assembly and you can write in assembly
people do Unix was originally written in
assembly and C language was created to
it was a higher level language above
assembly that they created Richie and
Thompson created C so that they had a
compilable language that would compile
to assembly the original compiler fory
had to be written in assembly see how
this works and then it would compile to
assembly and then you Unix right so they
were able to write Unix a lot faster the
goal of of adding a higher level
language is always developer speed
always it's not efficiency in terms of
performance it's always how fast can I
write this code okay and and that's
really important when you're evaluating
languages so I let's let's just regroup
here so at the very low level all all
code has to be assembled it has to be
you know has to run as assembly and the
way that it becomes that depends complet
vastly differently on the type of
language it is and as I said you have
the tree over here and the tree over
here you have you have the compiled
languages the statically typed languages
that end up the end result becomes you
know an elf binary which is machine code
more or less uh you know with resource
forks and stuff and and then you have um
you know other languages that create
intermediate steps to get to that and
this is where stuff gets really
interesting I would love to draw you a
picture um I'm not but so so let's talk
about specific languages I already told
you about C so C is one step up from
assembly okay you might be wondering
where is rust rust is one step up from
assembly okay you write rust it compiles
it becomes essentially assembly code
okay there's no intermediate
step and um and then it depends on what
kind of speed you're talking about right
you're talking about when people talk
about speed they always mix up a bunch
of things we're talking about developer
velocity how fast you can write code
versus how fast does it execute versus
how fast does it start up those are all
important considerations okay so let's
stick with the languages so C is One
Step Up rust is One Step Up guess what
else is one step up go go is One Step Up
Above assembly the difference between
rust and and go fundamentally at that
point is how much runtime does it have
like how much abstraction is built into
the languages because because you know
the way that it writes its assembly the
way that it gets generated the method of
taking it from you know source code to
assembly is radically different and the
you know and how you deal with different
things how you deal that's where things
like garbage collection come in that's
where you know things like um
asynchronous programming like doing two
things at once that's parallelism um you
know and how do you get around that
those all of those strategies are
implemented by the language and that but
they all that those strategies get
implemented ultimately in some kind of
runtime engine at the lowest level you
got to be careful with the word runtime
engine in this case because that can
mean lots of things in different context
but right now it means that is what gets
you know run that's how your code gets
run and so the big debate between rust
and go is over garbage collection which
is a very complicated thing for a
beginner but what It ultimately means is
am I hanging on to memory or am I so is
the is the programmer releasing the
memory exclus exclus you know or is or
is my my program taking care of memory
management and why would you care
because the memory management is what
makes you efficient as a developer the
reason it's reason people can code and
go faster than than rust is because
memory management right the the the more
abstract uh your engine is the more
magic it does for you the faster you can
write in it because it's doing more
things for you and therefore the syntax
becomes simpler it becomes easier to
write easier to understand there's no
nobody on the planet including the
biggest rust Advocates will tell you
rust is easy to understand they won't
tell you C is easy to understand either
right and C++ is just you know a
different way to write C but It
ultimately becomes you know the Same by
code I'm not by code assembly code Bode
is a different thing completely I
misspoke there we're going to get to
that so um so so you have the different
approaches and you have the different
compile things so that's those are the
fundamental differences between rust so
the reason that people who do low-level
operating system buzzing like gamoo who
is a Defcon you know guy um the reason
they like rust is because they can write
an entire operating system you know very
quickly that does exactly what they want
that doesn't have a lot of extra magic
in it and they love that they love that
that's why rust is in the Linux kernel
now that's why people are propo propos
you know proposing that it be more
replacement for C because it is safer
you can't you can't you know a lot of
times you have to turn off the safeties
in order to get anything done and in
that of of you know shared pointers are
are the fastest way to get anything done
and that's fundamentally against the
unsafe Paradigm anyway I'm getting
really down and dirty with that but now
you're learning okay well what about the
other languages what about Java which is
what triggered this conversation what
about python what about JavaScript what
is Javascript is Javascript the same as
Java what about go what about you know
all these other L Crystal Julia any of
them so all the other languages have
different purposes and they but they all
fundamentally end up with assembled code
on the bottom and there's going to be at
least one person who programs on python
out there that's going like wait a
second my code's not compiled it
actually is compiled so let let's talk
about this so when the difference
between a compiled a statically compiled
language these days you as I said
they're all compiled so saying a
compiled language as a distinction is
kind of problematic right because
they're all compiled every single
language is compiled everyone the
difference is is that usually in common
terminology when somebody says it's
compiled what they mean is that the that
the result is they get a binary they
usually get an elf binary which is a
collection of assembly and other things
um but they get it's called an elf
binary usually on Unix so they get a
binary right and that binary has to be
written that binary has to be created
for a specific architecture that means
that that you can't run a compiled rust
or go program or C program you cannot
run it on something for which it was not
made you can with a Python program and
we're going to get to why that is so a
Python program can do that okay so so
but when you're talking about C we talk
C Crystal Julia um any of the cing stuff
you know um all these languages are
compiled and and in this sense it's a
more general term it means that you get
a binary out of it you can't run the
code until you create a binary and
that's true in any case but in this case
it's it's it's it's is referring to the
fact that as a part of the regular
development workflow you are going to
compile the code
yourself and this the fundamental
difference between those languages and
the non-compounded languages the
interpreted languages is that The
Interpreter compiles it for you at
runtime is and we're get to there's lots
of variations on that so that means that
you have um code that is being compiled
for
you and so this is why people who write
in python or node or or whatever there
even Java Java Java's kind a very
interesting case that's why I'm talking
about it so Java's kind of both it it it
Bridges the gap between the two we're
going to talk about how that works but
so so you know python JavaScript
typescript
Ruby um what's another one
ala all of these languages are just in
time compiled what that means is that
when you run it The Interpreter is like
oh you want to run this thing bash same
thing bash zshell all of those all of
the shell languages T shell those are
all interpreted which means there's an
interpreter The Interpreter is the
compiled thing when you run an
interpreted language uh interpreted code
and we almost always a a code that is
interpreted is not called a program it's
almost always called a
script and in the industry people use
the term script to distinguish between
compiled code like rust C C++ Java so
the difference between a script and a
program in this sense you can think of
bash and go this is why we learned both
of them in the terminal velocity boost
because bash is an example of an
interpreted scripting
language and go is is an example of a
compiled
language ajango web app is extremely
complicated that that that is a little
bit of everything but ultimately it's
interpreted okay so PHP is interpreted
um PHP is
interpreted uh what I saying um what was
the other one God any any of the web
stuff is all
interpreted and and what does
interpreted mean interpreted means
there's an interpreter involved okay so
let's talk about what an inter
interpreter is um an
interpreter is compiled so you remember
I said you can't run anything on a
program that's not
compiled The Interpreter is compiled you
remember I talked about how rust and go
you know Implement their own runtime
kind of abstractions internally within
the compiled binary itself they have
their own whether they you know garbage
collect memory or any of these things
they have these they have these like
rules about how stuff should run that
end up in every one of the binaries
right but that's where but they're kind
of encoded into the binary um an
interpreter takes care of all of that so
The Interpreter decides whether how to
handle memory and all that stuff the
interpr in an interpreted language The
Interpreter is what runs The Interpreter
is compiled
code whether you know it's Dino or or
whatever it The Interpreter itself is
compiled code so in that sense you can
think of The Interpreter for python the
inter for any language is the
equivalent of the final product of a go
a c or a rust compilation in other words
when you compile code using rust or or
go or C or you are creating a
binary I mean it does something
different completely but it is
fundamentally the same thing yeah lbm
ASM Java yeah j y so at the lowest level
at the lowest level the the binary that
you create by compiling go
yourself is the
same essentially as the python
interpreter obviously they do two
radically different things but the
nature of
their you know if you were to open the
files up right the binary files that get
created you would see that they're both
in the case of Unix and Linux they're
both elf binaries they both have the
same thing so you could you could you
know if you're examining them as a
forensics person they would look similar
they're doing different things but they
are the same C is in the Java land for
sure okay we're going to talk about C
and Java in a second because those are
very very python actually is in that
same group so Okay so we've talked about
interpreted languages and we've talked
about compiled languages right so in the
case of interpreted languages I'm going
to repeat it The Interpreter is the
thing that's compiled you say but Mr Rob
you said all code is compiled it
actually is so here's here's the kicker
when you run a Python program or a node
program JavaScript typescript when you
run any of these programs and this by
the way includes C and Java we're going
to get there you are not running that
code I know that seems weird right
you're absolutely not running that
code that code bash same thing that
interpreted code is being translated
into
instructions that go to The Interpreter
that tell the interpr preter what to do
and then The Interpreter goes you know
through assembly it talks directly to
the
system through mostly cisal and it tells
the system what to
do that's why it's called an interpreted
language because you are not doing
anything directly every single bit of
code that you've written never directly
hits the kernel ever it never does it
becomes
instructions that are interpreted by The
Interpreter and The Interpreter sends
those
instructions now I don't I don't you
don't have to be a genius to know that
that's going to be slower to execute
than a compiled program and that's one
of the fundamental differences that's
why people are all during during the the
the the late 90s and early 2000s
everybody was interpreter crazy because
they can write code interpreted
languages much faster than they can
write compiled code enter go and rust
and all the other you know multi we're
going to get there okay but Java was
King the late '90s the late '90s through
even now Java still is King why because
it was compiled but it's also
interpreted and this is why I had to say
all of this when somebody asked me if
JavaScript and Java are the same the
answer now I can describe to you and
maybe you'll understand it better
JavaScript is an interpreted
language but it's not compiled Java and
C are both C actually would have been
Java but Microsoft to ask if they could
do Java and they licensed it and Google
said No at the time they had they owned
it and and and they said fine we'll make
our own that's how C became a thing um
and otherwise they're almost identical
in syntax it's kind of cool I prefer CP
actually to Java but I haven't done it
in 20 years so Java Java came along and
it said look we want to make it more
efficient to take the instructions that
you write in code so we want to improve
the efficiency of the communication
between the code that you write and The
Interpreter right the whole thing about
parsing it you know parsing is very
expensive parsing and are um parsing you
know let say you write python right so
let's parsing all the python code and
turning it into instructions that have
to go to The Interpreter that's a very
intensive
operation and it has to
happen I I'll get to BU code in a second
by code which is a thing um that that is
a very intensive operation it's a very
intensive operation to parse the script
you know bash python JavaScript whatever
and turn it into instructions for The
Interpreter and then and then and then
hand off all those you know hand off all
those instructions to the to the
colonel so so the interaction you know
the step between being a
script and and being an instruction set
for The
Interpreter that that
interaction that is an interaction
because interpreted
languages that's one of the biggest slow
points right that's one of the places
where interpreted languages are really
really slow and Bash is like one of them
bash is ridiculously slow right because
there is no intermediate step there's
never been any work to optimize that
because let's talk about that for a
second this is really important so by
the way that's the difference between
JavaScript and Java so JavaScript by the
way is a completely different language
the only reason I'm just going to put
this in really quick the only reason
JavaScript is called JavaScript is
because Java had a 50 $500,000 marketing
budget is the most marketed language of
all time and everybody everybody was
talking about Java at the time uh it was
created Liv script was the original name
Brendan Ike was told you know with a gun
in his head you're going to change the
name to be Java because we want to you
know dub tail on the marketing of java
and everybody will think it permanently
confusing the entire world and it wasn't
for another decade before they changed
the name of JavaScript to ecas script or
whatever ecma script which nobody says
JavaScript to this day has since become
owned you know it was all Java was all a
sun thing not Google I misspoke earlier
Java Java was owned by some Microsystems
which was bought by Oracle when before
they died and now Oracle owns the
trademarks for Java and JavaScript which
is still a problem so that's that's the
history of java um Java has nothing to
do with JavaScript at all they're not
even JavaScript is closer to lisp than
anything else and and uh L if you're
wondering is also an interpreter
language um Oracle to release the
trademark hopefully they will so anyway
now but that's so now you know the
difference between Java and JavaScript
but there's actually a much bigger
difference and this is the part that
blows people's minds and it actually
blew our minds in the 90s this is why
everybody uses
Java um that I said under two
minutes I I am a fail I'm a fail if I
said that that so what are we on we're
on like a minute we're on 18 minutes
okay so I'm going to keep going you
can't stop
me
um now I just want to stop and start
over yeah please
no okay
so you think this is easy content I keep
going okay so all right
so I did say that oh my god let's get
for keep going okay so the difference
between um Java and
JavaScript Beyond you know the obvious
differences is bite code and so remember
that communicate that that that
connection that slow that slow point
between it being stuff you type and
stuff that instructions for The
Interpreter so that that is that's a
weak point and so the attention in the
9s was on how can we speed this up by
the way python wasn't even around when
python came out so I think I think I
think python probably gets the credit
for this but um I don't know I don't
know that that would be something
interesting to find out did did python
come up with bite
code um all right so here we go so you
have so what is bite code all right so
bite code is an intermediate step
between the the text that you type into
the file and the instructions that go to
The Interpreter it's an intermediate
step that is designed to optimize that
slow point the slow point is the parsing
the parsing of the script if you're
writing bash nobody cares right it's
like I don't care if it's an extra
millisecond I can wait around but there
are a lot of times where that speed to
execution you know from startup to
execution is a thing and this is all by
the way this is all startup time I mean
you run code you run C rust or go
compiled code that code gets injected
straight into the kernel memory not in
the kernel memory it gets stricted right
into system memory and it runs right
away because it is the instructions you
see what I'm going with this when you
when you use compiled code like rust and
go that's why this you know Lightning
Fast lightning fast to execute when you
run the you'll notice this if you if you
write a bash script or a JavaScript or
python something like that and then you
write you write the same exactly the
same thing and go or rust or C and you
just see how fast it takes your the
command to execute from the time you hit
enter until the time it runs when you do
any interpreted language there's a
noticeable delay I mean it's small but
it's noticeable right when you do
anything that's been compiled it's
instantaneous because sometimes it's
already in memory it's already been
pre-cached but so it's just okay do this
thing and it's like one six system call
signal and it does the thing okay so to
so you know the python people and the
Java people and everything they're like
how can we make it the parsing easier so
what they did is they created bite code
and um I think I think assemblers some
assemblers have B code as well but what
ass what B code is B code is this
language that only The Interpreter
understands that's the simplest way to
say it bite code is a language that only
The Interpreter understands that's been
optimized for The
Interpreter and it saves the
interpreter from the work of parsing the
human readable
text and so it's kind of a
precompilation and so people when people
talk about compiled it's confusing
because to create bite code guess what
you compile
it B code is compiled you know so when
you say compiled you got to be careful
because the word
compile to some people means okay I'm
going to end up with an assembly you
know assembly code in an El binary
that's going to run straight in the you
know system memory if you're running C
rust or you know go but compiled to a
python person to a Java person means
that you're creating bite code that
means you're taking that text code that
you wrote and it's turning into bite
code and then the bite code next time
you run the program there's this thing
where it knows that the bite code is
there yeah jit jit well we already
talked about jit right we we talked
about it a little bit but we'll talk
about it again so um so so just in time
jet jit is that right so jit what what
that stuff does is it
it takes the bite codee and you know
creates it dynamically so so this this
is where things get really interesting
right and you actually have a setting
I'm going to show you a setting on
python uh that will might maybe help you
um instead of for metal yeah oh God we
don't we don't want to talk about that
we we want we're not even going to talk
about virtual machines no we're not that
that's like that's going to mess
everybody up they're going to be
totally yeah that that that no just know
that there's like when when you start
talking about a virtual machine versus a
real machine there's an entirely new
layer of abstraction that's a really
really really low level abstraction that
that you almost never need to worry
about you should probably know that
that's exists that's how people make it
happen somebody came around and
magically made uh made it so that you
could you know run binary code like as
if you're running a host operating
system as software and they basically
they emulated the entire Hardware layer
as software using EXT extremely
optimized low-level things it's just so
crazy complicated you don't ever need to
know about it um yeah so a virtual
machine is just a machine that's running
a software but really quickly and and it
started out as just pure software and
that's a type two hypervisor and then
they made Hardware versions of it that
can run it it which is a type one we
don't want to go down that rabbit hole
right now it's really interesting though
but that's how they do it um yeah
virtualization to most people is just a
black box so um so let's go back I want
to show you the setting here so you see
this here python don't write bite
code okay so what that what would that
setting even mean that means that my
python is slower why because normally
python does an extra step what python
does when you run it for the first time
it's slower because it has to compile to
python by code if you unless you set
this and it it makes this python by code
and then every time you run the program
from that on it doesn't run your program
well it does it checks to see if your
program changed it needs to be
recompiled before it uses the B code
which itself is a slow step right and
then it says okay no this is this bu
code hasn't been changed we're all good
there's the time stamp on the file and
the time stamp on the bu code is the
same therefore let's just send the Biko
to interpreter because it's faster this
all happens at lightning fast speed but
you know speed of light literally but
you know it says it says to The
Interpreter interpreter's like okay you
know what am I going to do now and it
does it processes the bite code turns
the bite code into instructions really
quickly because it doesn't have to do
any parsing and it it improves your
execution time a little
bit all of this stuff the only purpose
for any of this is to optimize startup
time that's it all of these
optimizations they're only to do one
thing to make the program run faster or
start up faster not run faster start up
faster because ultimately all of it ends
up in in in you know to be system call
messages and stuff like that to
communicate with the colonel and tell
them what to do they're all doing the
same thing in the end right and whether
one is fast or another is more about how
they send those instructions to the
computer not not about the fact that
they are now finally instructions to be
processed by the computer the the
startup time the speed comparison is
based on what have these different
languages done to to speed up the of
time and honestly it's kind of
interesting because there's been so much
effort focus on doing that startup C
there's one other reason to do bite code
and this is why Java is everywhere the
the one other reason to do that
intermediate step
between you know text that you write and
something that runs on the computer or
the interpreted instructions that get
run the one other reason to do that and
Java paid $500 $100,000 to market the
crap out of this because it's such a big
deal sayp C is the same thing is because
now they can say stupid stuff like this
write your code once compile it and run
it
anywhere I want you to think about that
for a second because it's one of the
biggest lies in technology that's ever
happened and and I'll tell you why
that's a lie later it's actually one of
the biggest frauds in all of Tech
History
the idea is that you will write your
Java program and that compiled bite code
I know Java runs on lots of devices it's
important but the idea that you would be
able to write you this is what they sold
us and it was a lie it was a huge lie
and I'm going to tell you why it was a
lie and I'm going to back that up in a
second I think it was 500,000 yeah so so
it's the only it's the only language
that ever had a marketing budget by the
way in history
Java and that's why so many people
adopted it so the network is a
computer somebody's old they remember
all the marketing we were all told that
these little tiny network devices were
going to be the only thing we ever
needed because everything was going to
be Java because what it was the idea is
this the idea is is that you you create
bite code and that bite code can run on
anything that has a jbm a Java virtual
machine what is a Java virtual machine
it's an interpreter all right it's an
interpreter it's not a virtual machine
it doesn't deserve the name virtual
machine it never did deserve the name
virtual machine it never had low-l
access to the devices and never could
because it doesn't have
unsigned pointer types but we'll get
into that later it was one of the hugest
lies in history and it still makes me
angry because they got everybody to use
Java based on this they told everybody
that yeah for people use your product
agreed so they they told everybody to
use Java because all of the
people Jesh from Silicon Valley actually
says this all right hi you know high
order functions this is this is almost a
direct quote from from Silicon Valley
when denes has asked whether he should
still have a job he's like I write high
order scol of functions that run on
anything if you haven't seen those those
Snippets from YouTube about denesh and
giloy both talking about why they should
have a job you should watch it it's very
interesting and they they they're
they're very accurate in what they say
it's pretty interesting so that's what
Tesh does he's a Java coder and he codes
high order functions that run on
anything what this means is he spends
his time dealing with business problems
like what does this code purpose what's
it going to do instead of where is it
going to run and how is it going to be
optimized and all that and that's skill
foil's job so as long as you can install
The Interpreter that's the catch as long
as they'll run on anything the the idea
that it will run on anything
is a lie and the actual statement is
that will run on anything with a
compatible jbm
[Music]
interpreter think about what that
requires that means any one of your
computers that's going to run the code
that you wrote has to have an
interpreter for that code and the
biggest problem with interpreted
languages and this this is the reason
you see python virtual machines why
don't you have a a PBE a python virtual
environment why don't you have a ruby
virtual environment why why why don't
you have a Java virtual
environment the reason these things came
into existence was because of the lie
and the LIE is that you only have to
install one interpreter on any computer
or device to run python to run Java to
run any interpreter language Ruby and
that turned out to be a huge lie because
as soon as they started creating
Divergent libraries and stuff
that things that were people were using
that didn't work with a particular
version of an interpreter you can see
where this
goes
right this so the LIE is and so what did
you end up getting yeah I I can't I
don't even want to talk about it make
give me
PTSD so the the lie that the Java mostly
the Java people sold on sold on the
whole world was right once run anywhere
as long as you have a compatible jbm
[Music]
interpreter and so the idea is that you
would have you would lock down The
Interpreter on a machine you would lock
down a version of of a Java interpreter
on a given machine and all of the code
that would ever run on that machine
would all be compatible with that that
thing and anybody who spent anytime in
the industry knows that that was that
was doomed to failure from the second
they tried it because it's impossible
and by the way this exact same problem
this exact same problem is happening
right now in
kubernetes and I'm just going to dub
tail I'm going to I'm going to tangent
on this right now the exact same design
disaster is happening right now with
kubernetes currently at work we are
running a kubernetes cluster that is no
longer it's been end of life it's now 3
years
old and the reason is because of all the
dependencies from all the Enterprise
applications on a specific version of
kubernetes in this sense kubernetes is
the virtual machine it's The Interpreter
kubernetes to in a to at an AR
Enterprise architectural level
kubernetes is an interpreter
it's an Enterprise interpreter that's
running Enterprise applications which
are these massive huge things that are
built up of lots of components but the
design principle is the same and what we
get we we had this problem we had Domino
we had to kick Domino out because they
wouldn't upgrade to use the latest
version of kubernetes which held us back
on kubernetes version so we had to kick
out the entire Domino project in order
to upgrade the problem is the same the
design principle is the same it's flawed
the idea that you can write code that
will compile to bite code and that that
bite code will be compatible with every
single you know device and that those
devices will all have the same
interpreter that will interpret the bite
code the same way is a lie it's a lie
and it's at this point it's been
established to be an antipattern it is
so much of an anti-pattern that that
there have been books written about it
about how bad it is and yet you know the
entire entirety of kubernetes is based
on the same anti pattern
I know I think it's a lie you own the BM
and the BM is open source and it runs
all the major US yes so so let's get
back to the jbm thing so what does c
does the same thing C I already told you
is it's just compiled with a bu code and
that bu code runs on anything with ABM
let let me tell you how the industry
tried to fix this problem they said and
I was w i i was firsthand witness of
this they said okay this bite code only
runs on this version of this
interpreter I said okay well if that's
the case I don't I don't want to I can't
trust to that that you know the lie that
that the jbm is going to be already
installed I can't trust that it's going
to be there so the obvious fix of that
is to bundle it with it well Java was
never intended for that Java was never
intended the whole point of java was
we're going to put a lot of stuff we're
going to make this huge big wonderful
jvm that's got you know Graphics
capabilities and all kinds of stuff
we're going to put it in this massive
virtual machine machine this interpreter
that it's going to be installed you know
pre-installed on all these devices that
was the Assumption and that meant that
the code that you wrote would be really
really tiny but you know they wanted to
make sure to put everything in the
kitchen sink in the virtual machine
because the idea was you wouldn't ever
install another one right which is
completely opposite of modern Computing
now it's all like only put the stuff you
need in the binary that's why go and
rust and everything have blown up it's
kind of a spoiler earlier but that's
what's happened so they said we so they
you know they're Ultra paranoid so what
they ended up doing is they ended up
putting everything into the virtual
machine they put so if you installed a
jbm on a on a server to do things that
didn't have anything to do with Graphics
it didn't matter your jbm you're was
bloated with all this crap that was
never going to get ever even used and so
you get this massive jbm binary that
that has to be present on the machine
for your stuff to run along comes some
smart person who says you know what I
don't know what version of jbm I have
therefore I'm going to bundle a jbm with
my chat
application and you think I'm kidding
that's what same time was load the same
time and and then the whole world went
crazy the whole world went crazy and
they said well if you're going to bundle
a virtual machine with yours then I
don't know my VPN connection app that
has a tiny little gooey needs to bundle
the entire jbm do anybody know of
another place that this is happening
right
now anything
anything there's another place that this
is happening electron yep you got it so
so I we're not going to talk about
electron we agree not to talk about it
so the the whole world just went nuts
and and all of a sudden these tiny
little applications that should probably
be a few megabytes are huge they're like
2 gigabytes because every one of them
has bundled the exact version of the
Java virtual environment that they
needed for their application even though
some of these appli are running with
exactly the same bundle jbm as somebody
else and those applications are all
consuming memory because they're not
designed to be installed or cached
they're actually using extra memory it
was a disaster it's probably one of the
biggest disasters in all of history and
we still haven't learned the problem the
lesson where it seems like we're kind of
learning it so this is where python
comes in so python had the same problem
right how many times have you been on a
system and you can't have python 2 or
Python 3 or python 4 there's no python 4
that's a
joke you have to have the right python I
can't run my program I have the python I
can't even run python to check if I have
the right version of python therefore I
okay I know I know I'll ship python with
my program that now you have python
virtual environments this is why I go up
every time I see
it and then Ruby has the same problem
like H we can't be sure they're going to
have the right interpreter so we'll ship
The Interpreter
we're going to ship The Interpreter with
our language so all of the interpreted
languages all failed at the same time
and to this to this day we're still
experiencing this failure because and
and a you know about
2013 some smart people started to think
about this and they're like you know
what this all this bundling of like
interpreters with the thing is really
just a symptom of a bigger problem what
if we just you know what if we made a
language that was statically tied I mean
statically compiled which meant that it
didn't have dependencies on being on a
particular system it's a lowlevel thing
let's make statically compiled programs
and let's write let's write software
let's write a new language or two or
five that can be compiled for Windows
even though it's being compiled on a Mac
or a Unix machine it's called cross
compilation it's like if if if if we
know the binaries that are going to end
up going in you know linking multi
together and everything if we know
what's going to end up in the final you
know elf binary that has to run on a
Target operating system why not just why
not just statically compile it's
called why not statically compile you
know and sure these sure these programs
are going to be bigger than their you
know their Boomer you know ancestors
that counted on compiled code being
already on the system dynamically linked
libraries that's what they're called and
so Along Comes you know Along Comes
these smart people and they're like you
know you know we we have more memory now
what if what if we just you know we got
rid of this this
craziness and we so sure the binaries
are going to be a little bit bigger but
they're not going to be nearly as big as
a Java app with a jbm bundled inside of
it you're going to be a fraction of that
size and so the world's like you know
because we had just gone through the
pain of bundle jbms and stuff that we
decided and it was even worse than that
by the way so it got to the point where
it wasn't even just a jbm it was an
entire Eclipse IDE built into it I'm
looking at you same time and Lotus Notes
I just cannot believe the level of bloat
it just went nuts and so Along come you
know the people like you know what in in
the face of this disaster um not even
kidding they they bundled the entire
Eclipse ID inside of it they they they
put the Eclipse engine sorry not the ID
eclipse is is is individual development
also has a it's an environment right so
you can code to it and everything so it
has it's like a collection of libraries
and stuff in addition to a jbm so
there's like yet you know even more
bloat right so you're bundling the
Eclipse engine you can go read about it
bundle the entire Eclipse engine inside
of it which includes a
jbm for your chat app it was so stupid H
yeah it's it's it's like it's more than
just yeah it's it's it's insane anyway
so in the in the face of this absolute
Insanity Along come some you know
Champions one of those being you know
Ken Thompson and Rob Pike who made C and
Unix to begin with and like what the
hell is happening we can't do this
anymore and and they started saying the
people who did Rush the same thing
they're like we need to start thinking
about cross-compiled statically linked
binaries and we need to rethink this
entire idea of interpreted languages
completely is the reason for the inter
all the things that they sold us in an
interpreted language about being able to
just write it really quickly and run it
anywhere and you know all of that are
now becoming we now see how painful they
are you can't run python anybody who's
done this today has this problem when
you try to run a nodejs Thing If for
your LSP for neam or something what you
got to do you got to install node.js
right instead of just downloading the
plugin and having it work because it's
compiled you have to like install
node.js to just run your LSP so that you
can write go code which is totally
screwed up my opinion so I have a no. JS
dependency in order to write my go code
because the LSP engine depends on an
interpreted
language okay so um management to be
nice yeah just in the folder it's not
though do you guys remember when node.js
like ran out of space and they and
Facebook had to make they made a whole
different thing than npm because the
node management modules was out blew
up that's why yarn became a thing I I
mean we could go all we could talk all
day about all the failures of
interpreted languages the one thing
that's overwhelmingly true that almost
nobody will realistically debate at this
point is that interpreted languages have
a ton of
plaws they have a ton of flaws and their
biggest flaw is you have to have it on
the system I wrote I wrote autoc
compliance software that had to run on
52,000 Machines of all different
operating system types and I used a
thing called pear exe that would bundle
the entire the entire peal thing inside
of it so that it could be executed and
every time it was executed I kid you not
it would it would uncache the the binary
executable stick it into a temp
directory set up a a pearl bright
virtual environment and then it would
run the Pearl code and then it would
interpret the Pearl code which meant
including bite code there was no bite
code for Pearl and then it would run it
and then it would come back with his
results all on one execution so when I
see something like go which is just a
single statically compiled binary it's
like gloriously paradise for me I can
write go code that will run on any
Target operating system in modern
existence and I can compile it ahead of
time so there there's no B code there's
nothing there's nothing but system calls
there's nothing but direct interaction
with the host system that's it and
that's why all of the languages that's
why the rust to go the C the C C++
that's why they have all seen Resurgence
that's why you're starting to see they
they came along with a with a technology
called the low-level virtual machine
llvm M which is basically the same idea
of virtualization except for it's at a
really really low level so it happens
inside of the binary and then based on
that you saw a lot of languages spring
up sang Julia Crystal and they're all
doing basically the same idea but
they're doing it and the result is you
get you get a binary that can run they
still have abstractions happening
they're just happening in the binary and
not an interpreter so they don't have to
be installed you can just run it
and you don't have to install an
interpreter or or bundle an interpreter
with your app which is totally stupid
nobody should ever do that anybody who
ever bundles and interpret your app
should be fired on the spot that is the
stupidest decision people have ever made
and ever will make they continue to make
that decision and perpetuate this bad
practice which we've all disagreed is
kind of a big nightmare that we just
want to wake up from okay and that
includes you know all the things
all you have to do is look at any system
and see all of its different versions of
thank God containers came around right
because I we can't talk about this
without not talking about containers
containers were a way to say okay we're
going to isolate a little tiny operating
system uh oh that compile time and gets
and gets gets lower to Target AR
machines Cod casually does it okay nice
yeah the L lbm but the point of lvm by
code is that is that it is really really
really low level and it ends up the the
result the result is that you get a an
executable program right it is self the
uses lvm is slightly slower than
compiled SEO or rust but you know the
abstraction is still happening within
the binary and not a separate
interpreter and you know that has to be
installed or or bundled you know you
know in inside of the thing that's a
very long description that's probably
God is that how long was that a
45-minute description of how languages
work so let's just run down all the
languages this is why I don't like
interpreted languages other than pres
scripting uh JS and python are still
killing way to learn code from my
experience especially JS and node
ecosystems I agree completely and the
reason that I am now approaching
teaching people to code by teaching them
bash which is the highest level possible
scripting language and and and um by
high level I mean really approachable by
humans you use it your entire
interaction with the shell is coding at
the highest possible level that's what
bash is it's the possible programming
language in terms of like not power but
just like how easy it is to write and
then the lowest and then we're going to
we're going to deal with a an
approachable low-level language which is
what go is rust is a low-level language
it's not approachable for a beginner
neither a c honestly I I do think you
should learn those languages but I
they're not approachable so I I'm I'm
you know hypothesizing that bash plus go
is a really great approach now I used to
teach python I used to teach JavaScript
which are interpreted language languages
they are valuable I think they should be
used for their domains and they are not
for the command line or for the terminal
I mean python kind of is a weird one I
don't want to get into it but the reason
python is used for machine learning and
stuff is because people that are doing
machine learning and data science on
with python are technically not using
python they're using C and C++ and
python is just really good at
masquerading and helping see masquerade
as some nice happy language that's what
python is and the reason py gets all the
credit for machine learning it's not
because people people are writing really
awesome machine learning code in in
Python they're not they're they're
writing they're writing they're writing
the engines the numpy and you know
tensor flow and Pi pytorch those are all
written in C and
C++ and then python is and python has
been really popular python has one
superpower python python is like the guy
who's who's who's good with memory
charms in Harry Potter he's not a really
good
wizard but he's really good at making
you think he's a good
wizard by tricking your memory do python
python is really really good at covering
up the ugliness of writing C directly
and and so it's super popular with data
science and academics and and machine
learning people because they can take
the slow parts of their python code and
then they can speed them up by writing
just those parts in C and then they can
inject it they can also do that in go
and rust and other languages they don't
though python has become the most
popular um sort of you know surface
language because it does have a very
approachable syntax despite its
widespace problems and thing so so
that's that's what's with python that's
why python is what is it the number two
most popular language right now um thank
you for the sub so so that's that's
that's why it's it's a thing uh and
quite honestly it is pretty damn cool
the way it does that um so I it's been
one of my my bullet points to learn for
a long time is like how do you how do
you speed up your python uh python is to
get stuffed un language that's why you
know hackers and coders love it they
also love Ruby and pearl for that reason
Pearl Pearl is not meant to be in that
same category it's meant to more more of
a command line language it always has
been um people people you know say bad
thing I have this whole video about
Pearl you can go watch by is kind of an
inversion of control in the game engine
you might Ed Lua so the people yeah Lua
is the most embeddable language on the
planet and now that we're seeing more
people write configure ations that have
logic in them uh despite the security
implications it's l is really shining
and uh I'm a huge fan of Lua for that um
I use you know Western because it's got
Lua config I use neoen because it's got
Lu config when I when I needed it you
know otherwise I use MIM script on some
random system um I am surprised the
problem with I'm actually really really
glad that Lua is dethroning python as a
configuration language um quite honestly
I I think they probably should have done
anible and Lua can you imagine that if
they had done ansible in Lua it would
have been so amazing somebody needs to
make
that somebody needs to remake anible in
Lua Lua is the absolute best possible
language if for that if I don't know
very much of it but if they had done
anible and terraform and Lua instead of
hash aore configuration
language yeah like L that wasn't so
weird I know I do
too the language design I I like it the
whole one thing I can get over it I
complain about it all the time but I'm
pretty new to Louis so I have I know
stay tuned um it tables in one is such a
terrible design well yeah it is a
terrible design but it's it's a good
design for something that's a
configuration language which is what it
always was right if you're if you're
it's a really really really great
configuration language I think um you
know what I mean I I think for
configuration it's way better than yaml
and
Json and and I'm I'm kind as I said I'm
kind of early into it maybe I haven't
got burned yet badly Enough by yeah um
you don't have logic you don't have
logic in and processing you know and
function the ability to write a function
in Json or yl and I I find that to be
extremely unfortunate so I I think I
think if the developers of kubernetes
had looked closer at Lua that you would
we would have been able to avoid Helm
charts
altogether and I you know anyway so I'm
kind of diverting there hopefully that's
been a good enough overview um I'm going
to go ahead and call that holiday Boost
number 7 or whatever and I know that was
kind of out of order but I'm going to
definitely put this in the list of
educational things for the day
particularly because it's an hour long
um and next already kind of does that
right though it doesn't have l y has ASO
you can write a function and try hard
yeah I don't know about that yeah I
don't know I'd have to try that um yeah
so anyway the takeaway from this video
is what are the different languages what
does it mean to be a compiled language
why is Java still a thing why is it used
and by the way the one thing I want to
end on is all of that Insanity it all
happened for one reason everybody wanted
to make things start faster and they
believed in a false dream
I mean that's two
reasons they believed in the false dream
that they would be able to write code
and have it run anywhere which never
happened it never happened my friends
anybody that's been alive during that
time will tell you it never happened it
still hasn't happen it never will happen
so the answer is use a statically do use
a statically compiled language and those
languages are there's a very short list
of those languages that are used in
production today Go is is the number one
Enterprise all of the cloud native
Computing was made with go and I don't
want to make this a go versus rust video
because it's stupid they're totally
different goals but the reason that go
is just G to blow the world away and
already has kubernetes was made with it
Docker podman uh alasa search wasn't
alasa search was Jaa um what else Helm
um you know the entire Cloud native
World Vault was made in go because go is
basically a modern Java Java still is
really prevalent in places where the
control over you know the Java virtual
machine is in place in fact there's an
entire category of work where people are
writing variations of java they're not
even Java but they run on the Java
virtual machine because a lot of huge
companies have invested a lot in
building up infrastructure
based on the original dream of having
just one VM Java virtual machine that
runs on that device the entire stock
industry all you know the the finance
industry runs this way that's why
they're all Java the the insurance
industry places like that places that
had the ability to control you know
server software that's running in one
place and they had total control over
the over the everything about it those
things are running about they're running
that they're they are thank you they're
they're they're running Java and why are
they running Java and they are kicking
ass by the way they're just as fast to
see because their Java applications are
run they only have to start up once and
then they just keep running so Java is
still a very very
valid option for anything that is has to
continuously run Java is also the basis
of all Android devices where they have
full control over what the underlying
thing is they they don't write in Java
they write in cotlin which is a dialect
and so so it's probably important that
we conclude with this right because
you're going to hear about clure Scola
cotlin and a number of others these
languages are Java at the core what they
do is they compile into Java bite code
so they're not Java they're their own
languages but they compile into Java
bite code that runs on any jbm that's
compatible and so so you get languages
like culture and Scala which are huge
languages with the finance sector with
Enterprise with you know with insurance
agencies all these big companies you
know in that sense and in that sense
they you know they kind of they kind of
go with that um so anyway I I just I
just wanted to put that out there that
is what that is what is is driving this
right the thing that's driving the
reason it's still a great idea to get a
job on Java if you can code in I was
just we were actually having a
conversation about this and I I'll I'll
conclude with this if I were to go I'm
still very intrigued by schola and I
know a lot of really amazing developers
and human beings who have learned
closure and just made bank I mean
working for banks a lot of them they
they code in closure closure and Scola
are functional languages that work on
jbms and so the point of that is that oh
uh less has written at Scola yeah
Twitter is written at Scola I I
personally if if I had to learn another
language and I knew I wanted to get a
really good job and I wouldn't want to
shoot myself on the head writing in the
code every day but I wanted to learn a
language that I knew was going to pay
ridiculous amounts of money I would
learn Scala personally because because
Scola as I understand it I don't know
but as I understand it Scola is this
happy median between functional and
procedural programming in Java you don't
have to use class-based object Orient
programming at all the worst part about
Java is is is to use the words of people
who invented it is class-based
inheritance over
composition and if you're writing in
scholar which is a functional
programming language plus a little bit
of procedural closure is 100% perceived
functional language it only does
functional and therefore you know it
it's it's more of a you got to buy off
into the whole functional Paradigm which
is great but as I understand it and I
don't know I don't know but as I
understand it Scala is sort of a a happy
medium uh between um between functional
programming and and procedural
programming um I would if I was going to
if I was going to do any kind of Android
development or everything I would learn
cotlin for sure and cotlin feels a lot
like Swift which
is you know um Apple's interpreter Lang
anguage um cotlin is also not very
strictly typed in other words you don't
have to it's it's easy to write
apparently um so scal say similar
balance I probably like it yeah I I
think I I the reason I think I would
like Scala is because I think Scala has
the same functional plus procedural
balance you know that go has but it has
the jbm and so you're you're writing
code that runs in the jbm ecosystem and
the jbm ecosystem has money they got
billions of dollars and they pay dude go
search the the the opening quote the
opening quote from Silicon Valley where
he says and yeah we're changing the
World by creating elant hierarchies for
for Recon reasonable code elegant
hierarchies or whatever that quote came
from the Scola web page and I found that
out by accident I was reading about
Scola and I saw it on the web page you
can go back in the Wayback machine and
find it and I read it and I said oh my
God that's a direct quote from Silicon
Valley so Silicon Valley is pretty dated
it was back when Scola was really hot
and I was just asking my my AI if Scala
is still hot and she says it is she's
like yeah it's still getting used all
over the place so if you had to if you
had to if if you want to if you want to
learn Java because you know that's where
the money is and and and you don't mind
you know picking up a job you know
working in a a coating sweat shop for a
big bank or EC Corp or something then
yeah scull I would I would at least eny
it probably uh you can compile Java to
your machine code nowadays native image
aot compiler yeah yeah I'm I'm I I
haven't even looked at that I haven't
looked at that I think it would be
interesting I I think a lot of the those
lessons are are coming
around uh a takes over the office yeah
it's pretty funny yeah yeah there's
there's a lot of uh really great I we're
watching in Silicon Valley again right
now my wife and I it's really funny
anyway so that's the end of this holiday
boost I guess uh it started out as a
what it's going to be a two-minute video
am I ever capable of that no I'm not but
my throat is like hurting so I'm going
to stop talking um so yeah you know what
here's your homework go research all the
different languages out there you still
need to make a decision about what you
want to do with your
life and part of that decision could be
do I want to work for a big bank and
make a lot of money and you know go
camping on the weekend or do I want to
have work for a forest ranger my entire
life and learn whatever you have to
learn for that you know the technology
related to that um access to the job
Lottery is which is a large Pro
absolutely yeah um so hopefully that
that'll give you that all right that's
the end of that recording